Erik Blegvad Papers
University of Minnesota Libraries
Erik Blegvad Papers
1957-2000
University of Minnesota Libraries Children's Literature Research Collections
Blegvad, Erik
CLRC-779
The collection consists of production materials for 14 titles, including original art, proofs, typescripts and holographs.
Not known.
Important Information for Users of the Collections
Access and Use:
Collection is open for researchers with no restrictions. Registration with the collection is required.
Biographical Sketch
Erik Blegvad was born in Copenhagen, Denmark in 1923. He graduated from the Copenhagen School of Arts and Crafts in 1944. He served in the Royal Danish Air Force from 1945 to 1947. He has had a long career as an artist and illustrator. He immigrated to France in 1947 where he was a free lance artist. He immigrated to the US in 1951 where he became an illustrator of children's books. He immigrated to England in 1966 and returned to the United States in 1986. He has won numerous awards for his illustrations, mostly pen and ink. Biographical Source: Something About the Author, v. 132, pp. 17-22.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of production materials for 14 titles, including original art, proofs, typescripts and holographs.
Indexing Terms
The collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of the University of Minnesota Libraries. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Blegvad, Erik
Accession Information:
Erik Blegvad donated the collection over a period of time from 1972 to 2000.
Gift of: Blegvad, Erik
Arrangement
Diamond in the Window, 1962
Cat From Nowhere, 1969
Flivver, the Heroic Horse, 1958
Hans Christian Anderson: Stories and Fairy Tales, 1993
Late Spring, 1957
Miscellaneous original art,
Mushroom Center Disaster, 1974
Oddity Land, 1957
Speech,
Swing in the Summerhouse, 1967
Water Pennies, 1991
Hurry, Hurry Mary Dear, 1998
Sound of Leaves, 1996
Riddle Roads, 1999
Around My Room, 2000
Greatest Hamster Hunt, 1969
One is for the Sun, 1968
Collection Contents
- Diamond in the Window, 1962
  Langton, Jane
  New York: Harper and Row, 1962
  - Proof jacket, 1 p. (Box MC 251)
- Cat From Nowhere, 1969
  Stirling, Monica
  New York: Harcourt, Brace and World, 1969
  - Ink dummy with text proof, 56 p. (Box MC 1326)
  - Ink and watercolor illustration with text proof for jacket, 1 p. (Box MC 1326)
  - Ink dummy with text proof pasteups, 48 p. (Box MC 1326)
- Flivver, the Heroic Horse, 1958
  Kingman, Lee
  Garden City, New York: Doubleday, 1958
  - Sheet of 2 ink illustrations, 1 p. (Box MC 1326)
- Hans Christian Anderson: Stories and Fairy Tales, 1993
  London: Heinemann, 1993
  - Miscellaneous studies, 2 p. (Box MC 747)
  - Studies for body of book, typescript pasteups, 29 p. (Box MC 747)
  - Studies for cover/jacket, 18 p. (Box MC 747)
  - Photocopy of studies for cover/jacket, 4 p. (Box MC 747)
  - typescript, corrected photocopy, 26 p. (Box MC 747)
  - color page proofs, 45 p. (Box MC 747)
  - sheet suggested topography for cover, 1 p. (Box MC 747)
  - mock jacket illustrations, 2 p. (Box MC 747)
  - colored photocopies of cover, 2 p. (Box MC 747)
  - colored photocopies of endpapers, 2 p. (Box MC 747)
  - typescript, corrected, 58 p. (Box MC 1981)
  - typescript, corrected photocopy, 1 p. (Box MC 1981)
  - galley proofs, 2 p. (Box MC 1981)
  - correspondence, 12 p. (Box MC 1981)
  - layout notes, 7 p. (Box MC 1981)
- Late Spring, 1957
  Fritz, Jean
  New York: Coward-McCann, 1957
  - ink sketches for jacket, 6 p. (Box MC 1326)
- Miscellaneous original art
  - ink and watercolor greetings inscribed to Irvin Kerlan, 2 p. (Box MC 1326)
  - postcard, 1 p. (Box MC 1326)
  - greeting cards (Box MC 1326)
- Mushroom Center Disaster, 1974
  Bodecker, N.M.
  New York: Atheneum, 1974
  - ink dummy with text proof and watercolor jacket, 48 p. (Box MC 1326)
  - ink and watercolor illustration for jacket, 1 p. (Box MC 1326)
  - ink dummy, 48 p. (Box MC 1326)
  - photocopy of jacket, 1 p. (Box MC 1326)
  - sheet text proof for jacket, 1 p. (Box MC 1326)
  - sheets proof, 2 p. (Box MC 1326)
  - sheet correspondence, 1 p. (Box MC 1326)
- Oddity Land, 1957
  Anthony, Edward
  Garden City, New York: Doubleday, 1957
  - ink illustration, 1 p. (Box MC 1326)
  - sheet (3 ink illustrations), 1 p. (Box MC 1326)
- Speech
  - holograph, 6 p.
- Swing in the Summerhouse, 1967
  New York: Harper and Row, 1967
  - photostats fo illustrations for book, 21 p. (Box MC 251)
  - proof jacket, 1 p.
- Water Pennies, 1991
  New York: Macmillan, 1991
  - correspondence, 2 p. (Box MF 1981)
- Hurry, Hurry Mary Dear, 1998
  New York: Margaret K. McElderry Books, 1998
  - jacket proofs, 8 p. (Box MC 747)
  - dummy proofs, 43 p. (Box MC 747)
  - pen, paint jacket study, 1 p. (Box MC 747)
  - pencil, watercolor jacket study, 1 p. (Box MC 747)
  - pen jacket text sketches, 3 p. (Box MC 747)
  - pen, pencil jacket sketch, 1 p. (Box MC 747)
  - color page proofs, 2 p. (Box MC 747)
  - photocopy of jacket study, 1 p. (Box MC 747)
- Sound of Leaves, 1996
  Blegvad, Lenore
  New York: Margaret K. McElderry Books, 1996
  - pencil sketches, 19 p. (Box MC 747)
  - photocopy of pencil sketch, 1 p. (Box MC 747)
  - layout notes, 1 p. (Box MC 747)
  - watercolor, crayon cover study, 1 p. (Box MC 747)
- Riddle Roads, 1999
  Spires, Elizabeth
  New York: Margaret K. McElderry Books, 1999
  - pen, color pencil cover studies, 2 p. (Box MC 747)
  - dummy proof with jacket, 30 p. (Box MC 747)
  - page proofs, 4 p. (Box MC 747)
  - layout notes, 1 p. (Box MC 747)
  - jacket illustration, 1 p. (Box MC 747)
  - jacket page proofs, 2 p. (Box MF 1981)
  - correspondence, 24 p. (Box MF 1981)
- Around My Room, 2000
  Smith, William J.
  New York: Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 2000
  - pencil dummy, 26 p. (Box MC 747)
  - pen, typescript and pasted dummy, 51 p. (Box MC 747)
  - notes on first sketches, 3 p. (Box MC 747)
  - dummy proof with jacket, 32 p. (Box MC 747)
  - layout notes, 1 p. (Box MC 747)
  - cover studies, 10 p. (Box MC 747)
  - pen, color pencil, watercolor illustration, 1 p. (Box MC 747)
  - pen, pencil, watercolor illustration, 1 p. (Box MC 747)
  - jacket study, 1 p. (Box MC 747)
  - correspondence, 1 p. (Box MF 1981)
  - typescript, 32 p. (Box MF 1981)
  - page proofs, 5 p. (Box MF 1981)
  - layout notes, 1 p. (Box MF 1981)
- Greatest Hamster Hunt, 1969
  - typescript, corrected, 22 p. (Box MF 1981)
  - correspondence, 1 p. (Box MF 1981)
- One is for the Sun, 1968
  Blegvad, Erik
  New York: Harcourt, Brace and World, 1968
  - typescript, corrected, 3 p. (Box MF 1981)
  - dummy, 16 p. (Box MF 1981)
  - research material, 1 p. (Box MF 1981)